<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno Regni Caroli Regis Angliæ, Scotiæ, Franciæ &amp; Hiberniæ Decimo quinto. At the Parliament begun and holden at Dublin, the sixteenth day of March in the fifteenth year of the reign of our most gracious soveraign Lord Charles by the Grace of God of England, Scotland, France and Ireland King, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. To the high pleasure of Almighty God, and to the weal publick of this realm, were enacted, as followeth.</title>
            <title>Public General Acts. 1669.</title>
            <author>Ireland.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B24665</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99831909</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206621</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248500134</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing I337bA</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99831909</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99831909e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B24665)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206621)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1779:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno Regni Caroli Regis Angliæ, Scotiæ, Franciæ &amp; Hiberniæ Decimo quinto. At the Parliament begun and holden at Dublin, the sixteenth day of March in the fifteenth year of the reign of our most gracious soveraign Lord Charles by the Grace of God of England, Scotland, France and Ireland King, defender of the Faith, &amp;c. To the high pleasure of Almighty God, and to the weal publick of this realm, were enacted, as followeth.</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts. 1669.</title>
                  <author>Ireland.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[22] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Benjamin Tooke, printer to the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and are to be sold by Samuel Dancer book-seller in Castle-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Session laws --  Ireland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  Politics and government --  17th century.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Ireland --  History --  1660-1690 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-06 </date>
            <label>Renee Mayes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206621:1"/>
            <p>ANNO REGNI CAROLI REGIS Angliae, Scotiae, <hi>FRANCIAE</hi> &amp; <hi>HIBERNIAE</hi> Decimo quinto.</p>
            <p>At the Parliament begun and holden at <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Sixteenth day of <hi>March</hi> in the Fifteenth year of the Reign of our most Gracious Soveraign Lord CHARLES by the Grace of God of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> King, Defender of the Faith, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>royal blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
               <head>C R</head>
               <q>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</q>
               <q>DIEV ET MON DROIT</q>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>To the High pleasure of Almighty God, and to the Weal publick of this Realm, were Enacted, as followeth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>DƲBLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to the Kings most Excellent Majesty, and are to be sold by <hi>Samuel Dancer</hi> Book-seller in <hi>Castle-street</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:206621:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206621:2"/>
            <head>THE TABLE OF The Statutes Printed.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN Act to admit the Subject to plead the General Issue in Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations of Intrusion brought on the behalf of the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, and to retain his possession till tryal. cap, 1.</item>
               <item>An Act for abridging of Proclamations upon Fines to be leavied at the Common Law. cap, 2.</item>
               <item>An Act for the relief of Patentees Tenants and Farmers of Crown lands or other profits, or of lands within the Survey of the Court of Wards and Liveries in cases of forfeiture for not payment of their Rents, or other Service or duty. cap, 3.</item>
               <item>An Act touching the finding of Offices before the Escheator, &amp;c. cap, 4.</item>
               <item>An Act against Discontinuances of Writs of Error in the Court of Exchequer, and for the better expedition in giving judgment there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in. cap, 5.</item>
               <item>An Act for strengthning of Letters Patents past and to be past, upon any of His Majesties Commissions of Grace for the Remedy of defective Titles, &amp;c. cap, 6.</item>
               <item>An Act concerning Clergy. cap, 7,</item>
               <item>An Act for punishing of Offendors within the county of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> against the Act for keepers of Ale-houses to be bound by Recognizance. cap, 8.</item>
               <item>An Act to discharge and free true men from all forfeitures for killing such as attempt to rob or murther them. cap, 9.</item>
               <item>An Act for remedy of errors and defects in Fines and common Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries heretofore leavied, acknowledged and suffered. cap, 10.</item>
               <item>An Act for endowing of Churches with Gleab lands. cap. 11.</item>
               <item>An Act concerning twentieth parts and other sums of money payable by persons Ecclesiastical. cap, 12.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="statutes_not_printed">
            <pb facs="tcp:206621:3"/>
            <head>The Statutes not Printed.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. AN Act for granting four entire Subsidies by the Temporalty.</item>
               <item>2. An Act for the granting of six entire Subsidies by the Prelates and Clergy of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. An Act for the better secureing of a Lease made by the Dean and Chapter of St. <hi>Patricks</hi> unto the Honourable Sir <hi>Robert Meredith.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. An Act that this Session of Parliament shall not determine by His Majesties Royal assent to this and some other bills.</item>
               <item>5. An Act to secure several and respective Estates to <hi>William Bulkley</hi> Priest in divers Lands in the Counties of <hi>Dublin, Wicklow</hi> and <hi>Kildare,</hi> or in some or one of them,</item>
               <item>6. An Act for securing of three Messuages or Houses with three Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens and one Orchard, with their appurtenances in St. <hi>Brides-street</hi> in the Suburbs of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> unto <hi>Anthony Dopping</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, his Executors, Administrators and Assigns, for the term of threescore years, beginning at the Feast of <hi>Easter,</hi> Anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni 1637.</item>
               <item>7. An Act for securing of certain Lands in the county of <hi>Wexford</hi> to <hi>George</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Fuernes</hi> and his Successors for ever: and also for securing of certain Lands in the said county to <hi>Nicolas Loftus</hi> Esq; his heirs and assigns for ever.</item>
               <item>8. An Act concerning the Lord Archbishop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Ʋsher</hi> Knight.</item>
               <item>9. An Act for the Settlement of diverse Lands and Rents in the Lord Archbishop of <hi>Dublin,</hi> the Lord Bishop of <hi>Elphin,</hi> and <hi>Nicolas Barnwall</hi> Esq; respectively.</item>
               <item>10. An Act for the Settlement of certain Lands, Rents and Tithes in the Lord Archbishop of <hi>Dublin</hi> and <hi>Richard Bealing</hi> of <hi>Cryhelp</hi> in the county of <hi>Wicklow</hi> Esq;</item>
               <item>11. An Act concerning <hi>Richard</hi> Earl of <hi>Cork</hi> and <hi>John</hi> Lord Bishop of <hi>Waterford</hi> and <hi>Lismore.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>12. An Act concerning the Lord Viscount <hi>Ranelagh,</hi> and the Lord Bishop of <hi>Elphin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>13. An Act for the Naturalization of <hi>Anthony, Francis</hi> and <hi>William Willoughby,</hi> sons of Sir <hi>Francis Willoughby</hi> Knight.</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:206621:3"/>
               <item>14. An Act for the Naturalization of <hi>Theodore Schout</hi> Merchant and <hi>Cornelius Schout</hi> his son.</item>
               <item>15. An Act for the Naturalization of <hi>Daniel Wybrants</hi> Merchant.</item>
               <item>16. An Act concerning the discharge of certain Rents, Services, &amp;c. due to His Majesty at <hi>Michaelmas</hi> in the year 1641, and for and untill the Feast of <hi>Easter</hi> in the year 1645.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:206621:4"/>
            <head>STATUTA, Actus, Ordinationes &amp; PROVISIONES</head>
            <p>EDita in secunda Sessione Parliamenti illustrissimi ac invictissimi Principis Domini nostri <hi>CAROLI</hi> Dei gratia <hi>Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiberniae</hi> Regis, fidei defensoris, &amp;c. virtute commissionis &amp; mandati dicti Domini Regis, sub magno sigillo suo <hi>Angliae,</hi> apud castrum <hi>Dublin,</hi> die <hi>Veneris,</hi> viz. vicesimo die mensis <hi>Martii,</hi> Anno Regni dicti Domini Regis <hi>Angliae, Scotiae, Franciae</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiberniae</hi> decimo quinto: Coram praedilecto &amp; perquam fideli Consanguineo &amp; consiliario suo <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma</hi> Comite <hi>Strafford,</hi> Vicecomite <hi>Wentworth,</hi> Barone de <hi>Wentworth Woodhouse,</hi> Domino <hi>Newmarsh, Oversley</hi> &amp; <hi>Raby,</hi> Domino Praesiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te Consilii dicti Domini Regis stabiliti in Boreali parte <hi>Angliae,</hi> Domino Locum-tenente Comitatus Eborum, uno de privato consilio dicti Domini Regis in <hi>Anglia,</hi> &amp; Domino Locum-tenente generali &amp; Gubernatore ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerali Regni sui <hi>Hiberniae,</hi> tento &amp; ibidem continuato us{que} ad diem <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curii,</hi> viz. decimum septimum diem <hi>Junii</hi> tunc proxime sequentis, &amp; abinde prorogato us{que} ad primum diem <hi>Octobris</hi> tunc proxime sequentis. Quod quidem Parliamentum virtute commissionis &amp; mandati praedicti, inchoatum &amp; primo tentum fuit apud praedictum castrum <hi>Dublin</hi> die <hi>Lunae,</hi> viz. decimo sexto die <hi>Martii,</hi> Anno supradicto, coram praedilectis &amp; fidelibus Consiliariis suis <hi>Roberto</hi> Domino <hi>Dillon</hi> &amp; <hi>Christofero Wandesford</hi> Armigero, tunc Dominis Justitiariis suis dicti Regni sui <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berniae,</hi> &amp; ibidem continuatum us{que} ad diem <hi>Mercurii,</hi> viz. decimum octavum diem ejusdem mensis <hi>Martii,</hi> &amp; adtunc prorogatum ad praedict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um castrum <hi>Dublin,</hi> us{que} ad praedictum vicesimum diem <hi>Martii,</hi> quo die praedicta secunda sessio praedicti Parliamenti inchoata &amp; tenta fuit &amp; ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terius prorogata prout supradictum est.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:206621:4"/>
            <head>ANNO XV. CAROLI REGIS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. An Act to admit the Subject to plead the General Issue in Informations of Intru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion brought on the behalf of the Kings Majestie, and to retain his possession till Tryal.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Here the Kings Majestie out of his Prerogative Royal, may enforce the Subject in Informations of Intrusion brought against him to a special pleading of his title, the Kings most Excellent Majestie out of his Gracious Disposition to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his loving Subjects, and at their humble suit being willing to remit a part of his ancient and Regal power, is well pleased that it be Enacted, And be it Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majestie, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by the Authority of the same, That whensoever the King, his Heirs or Successors and such from or under whom the King claimeth, and all others claiming under the same ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, under which the King claimeth, hath been or shall be out of possession by the space of twenty years, or hath not, or shall not have taken the profits of any Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, within the space of twenty years before any Information of Intrusion brought, or to be brought to recover the same: that in every such case, the Defendant or the Defendants may plead the General Issue, if he or they so think fit, and shall not be pressed to plea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> specially, and that in such cases the Defendant or Defendants shall reta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the possession he or they had at the time of such Information exhibited, u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>til the title be tryed, found, or Adjudged for the King. And be it further E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, That where an Information of Intrusion may fitly and aptly be brought on the Kings behalf, that no <hi>Scire facias</hi> shall be brought, whereunto the Subject shall be forced to a special pleading, and be deprived of the Grace in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended by this Act.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. An Act for Abridging of Proclamations upon Fines, to be leavied at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Law.</head>
               <p>WHereas a Statute made within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in the fourth year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Seventh, hath Ordained that every Fine to be leavied with Proclamations in the Kings Court, before his Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stices of the Common Pleas, should be proclaimed in the same Court that
<pb facs="tcp:206621:5"/> term in which it is ingrossed, and in three terms then next following, at four several days in every term, by reason whereof they ought to be proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med four times in every of the four several Terms, and that during the time of proclaiming of such Fines, all Pleas should cease, which to do according to the said Statute, considering the number of Fines which are like hereafter to be levied, would require several days in every Term, and be some preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and interruption to the Causes and Suits, in the said Court of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Pleas within this Kingdom, and also give occasions of sundry errors through the negligence and misprisions of Clerks, in mis-entring the same, and otherwise, whereby the Fines may be reversed: Be it therefore Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majestie, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parliament assembled, and by Authority of the same, that all Fines with Proclamations from and after the Feast of Easter next ensuing, to be levied in the said Court, shall be proclaimed only four times, that is to say, once in the Term wherein it is Ingrossed, and once in every of the three Terms, holden next after the same Ingrossing, and that every Fine proclaimed (as aforesaid) shall be of as great force and effect in Law, to all intents and purposes, as if the same had been sixteen times proclaimed, according to the Statutes heretofore made.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. An Act for the relief of Patentees, Tenants and Farmers of Crown lands or other profits, or of Lands within the Survey of the Court of Wards and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veries, in cases of forfeiture for not payment of their Rents, or other service or duty.</head>
               <p>FOrasmuch as the Kings Majestie out of his gracious disposition, is and ever hath been averse from taking any advantage, howsoever lawful and just, against any of his Subjects, growing by any forfeiture, breach of Condition, or strict interpretation of his Highness Grants, or Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, or the Grants or Letters Patents of any of his Royal Predecessors, of any Mannors, Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, and yet the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees or Patentees, deriving their Estates by or from his Majestie or his Predecessors, have been too apt and ready to exact the advantage of such for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture, where his Majestie himself or his Predecessors have not required the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ame, which hath been ever held an unequal and extream course, and hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>any times been relieved by Suits in Courts of Equity, though with the gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at charge and trouble of the parties indangered thereby: For remedy wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reof, aswell where the King or any of his Predecessors or Successors, have granted or shall grant the said Mannors, Lands, Tenements or Heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taments, or any part thereof, or the Reversion or any part thereof to any other, as where the Reversion, Remainder, or Estate thereof, is or shall be in the Kings Majestie or his Successors, in the right of the Crown of <hi>Ireland,</hi> or otherwise, his Majestie of his abundant grace towards his loving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, is gratiously pleased that it be Enacted, and be it Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majestie, by and with the Assent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same, that if any person or persons, Bodies Politick or Corporate, having, holding, or possessing, or which hereafter shall have, hold, or possess any Mannors, Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, by virtue or colour of any original Grant or Lease or Assignment of the same, made by the Kings Majestie or any of his Predecessors, or to be made by his said Majestie or any of his Successors, for any number of years, for Life or
<pb facs="tcp:206621:5"/> Lives, in Fee tail or Fee simple, or other Estate whereupon any Rent, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, or other duty hath been, is or shall be reserved or payable, with or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der any Condition or Limitation, of <hi>Reentry Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>er,</hi> or to be void for default of payment of such Rent, or performance of such Service or Duty, heretofore hath made, or any other by, from or under whom he claimeth, hath made, or any which hereafter shall have, hold or possess, shall make any default therein, and yet after such default made, such Rent, Service or other duty hath been or shall be answered, paid or done unto his Majestie or any of his Predecessors or Successors, into his or their Receipt of the Exchequer or Court of Wards, or to any other having Authority to receive the same, as the case shall require, before any advantage of such forfeiture, or cause of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feiture hath been or shall be taken, and before any Commission awarded to enquire, or other process issued touching the said forfeiture or non-payment of Rent, that in all such cases no advantage shall be taken by his Majestie, his Heirs or Successors, of, for or by reason of any such forfeiture or cause of forfeiture. And be it further Enacted, That no person or persons claiming, or which afterwards shall claim, by, from or under his Majestie, or any of his Predecessors or Successors, at any time after such cause or title of forfeiture given, shall in any wise have or take any benefit or advantage, by reason, means or colour of such default made or to be made, but that every such E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state forfeited or forfeitable, by means or occasion, of such default of payment of Rent or Performance of service, or other duty shall be adjudged to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue and have his being, as if no such default or cause of forfeiture had been had, or made, any Law, Custome, or Vsage, to the contrary thereof in any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. An Act touching the finding of Offices before the Escheator, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>WHere many and divers persons holding or that have holden Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, some for term of years, and some by coppy of Court Roll have been expulsed, and put off their terms and holds by reason of Inquisitions or Offices found before Escheators, Commissio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and others Containing Tenures of the King <hi>in Capite,</hi> intituling the King to the wardship or custody of such Lands or Tenements, by reason that such Leases for Term of years, or interest by coppy of Court Roll of such per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons have not been found in such Inquisitions or Offices after which expulsion or putting out the said persons have been without remedy for the obtaining of the said Farms, and holds, during the Kings possession therein, and can have no <hi>Travers, Monstrance de droit,</hi> nor other remedy for the same, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause their said Interest is but a Chattle in the Law, or Customary hold, and no Estate of Freehold, and also where any person or persons hath any Rent, Common, Office, Fee, or profit <hi>Apprendre</hi> of any Estate of Freehold, or for years or otherwise out of such Lands or Tenements, specified in such Office or Inquisition, the said Rent, Common, Office, Fee or profit <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prendre</hi> not found in the same Office or Offices, such persons are in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner without remedy to obtain or have the said Rent, Common, Office, Fee or profit <hi>App<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endre</hi> by any Travers or other speedy means, without great and excessive charges during the Kings interest therein, by force of such In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisition or Office: For remedy whereof, be it Enacted by Authority of this present Parliament, that where any such Office or Inquisition is or shall be found, omitting such titles, Interests or matters (as is aforesaid) that in all such Cases every Lessee, Tenant for term of years, or Copy holder,
<pb facs="tcp:206621:6"/> and every such person or persons that have or shall have any Interest to any Rent, Common, Office, Fee or other profit <hi>Apprendre</hi> for term of years, life or otherwise, out of any of the Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in such Office or Inquisition, where the King, his Heirs or Successors, is or shall be intituled as aforesaid, to any such Lands, Tenements or He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments, shall upon shewing and proving of his or their said title and interest in his Majesties Court of Wards and Liveries, have, hold, enjoy and perceive all and every their Leases and Interests for term of years, or by Copy of Court roll, Rents, Commons, Offices, Fees, and profits apprendre in such manner, form, estate and condition, as they and every of them should or might have done, in case there had been no such Office or Inquisition found, and as they should or lawfully might or ought to have done, in case such Lease, Interest or Copy of Court roll, Rent, Common, Office, Fee, or profit apprendre had been found in such Office or Inquisition, any Law, Custom or Vsage to the contrary heretofore used in such cases, in any wise notwithstanding. And also where it is or shall be found for the King, his Heirs or Successors, that the Heir or Heirs of his Tenant or Tenants, is or shall be within Age, where indeed such Heir or Heirs is or shall be at the same time of full Age, or of more or greater Age than is or shall be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained within such Office- Be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That in every such case such Heir and Heirs shall and may at his or their ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry full age or after, prosecute a Writ of <hi>Aetate probanda,</hi> and sue his or their Livery or Ousterlemain as his or their cases shall lie, and have the profits of his or their Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, from the time of his or their very full Age, any such untrue Office or Inquisition, or any Law or Custom to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. And also where one person or more is or shall be found Heir to the Kings Tenant by Office or Inquisition, where any other person is or shall be Heir, or if one person or more be or shall be found Heir by Office or Inquisition in one County, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other person or persons is or shall be found Heir to the same person in another County, or if any person be or shall be untruly found Lunatick, Idiot or dead; Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that every person and persons grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved or to be grieved by any such Office or Inquisition, shall and may have his or their Traverse to the same, immediately or after, at his or their pleasure, and proceed to tryal therein, and have like remedy and advantage as in other cases of Traverse upon untrue Inquisitions or Offices found, any Law, Vsage or Custom to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. And further, Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that where any Inquisition or Office is or shall be found by these words or like, <hi>quod de quo vel de quibus tenement. prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict. tenent. ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ator praed. ignorant,</hi> or else found holden of the King <hi>per que servic. ignorant,</hi> or such like, that in such case such Tenure so uncertainly found, <hi>de quo vel de quibus tenement. praed. tenent. ignorant.</hi> shall not be taken for any immediate tenure of the King, nor such tenure so found of the King <hi>per que servicia ignorant.</hi> shall not be taken any <hi>tenure in capite,</hi> but in such Cases a Writ of <hi>melius inquirendum,</hi> to be awarded as hath been accustomed in old time, any usage of later time to the contrary notwithstanding; but if upon the <hi>melius inquirendum</hi> it shall be found by these words or the like <hi>viz. de quo vel de quibus tenementa praedict. tenentur jurator. ignorant,</hi> or a tenure found of the King <hi>per que servicia ignorant,</hi> then in both these cases the same shall be held to be a tenure <hi>in Capite</hi> by Knights service, until such Offices shall be avoided by travers or otherwise. And be it further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, that where it is or shall be found by any Office or Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition, that any Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments, are or shall be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scended, remained or come to any Heir within age and in the Kings Ward,
<pb facs="tcp:206621:6"/> or that ought to be in the Kings Ward, and that such Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments are holden of the King immediately, where in Deed the same are or shall be holden of some other common person, and not of the King immediately: That in such case such Heir or Heirs shall and may have their Traverse to the same within age, and like remedy and restitution upon his or their title found or judged for him or them therein, as hath been accustomed and used in other cases of Traverses, any Law, Vsage or Custom to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. Also where the Kings Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty by his Prerogative ought to have as well such Lands and Tenements as be holden of other persons, as holden of himself immediately, whereof his Tenant holding of him in chief dieth seised, his Heir being within Age, untill such time as Livery be sued by such Heir, and that the mean Lords of whom the said other Lands and Tenements of such Heir be holden used to spare the Rents due to them for the same Lands or Tenements, holden of them during the Kings possession, and when such Heir hath sued his or their Livery, they use by distress or otherwise to compell the same Heir to pay to them the Arrearages of such Rents, for such time as the said Lands or Tenements were in the Kings possession by such minority where they should have sued by petition to the Kings Majesty, to have obtained the fame out of the Kings hands, if they would have the same, which is to the great detriment, loss and hindrance of such Heir and Heirs; for redress whereof, Be it Enacted by the Authority of this present Parliament, That from henceforth such mean Lords during such minority shall have, receive and take such Rents by the hands of such of the Kings Officers, Lessees o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tees, as shall be appointed to have, receive and take the issues, rents and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the same Lands and Tenements so holden of such mean Lord du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the minority and non-age of such Heir and Heirs, and untill such Heir and Heirs sue his or their Livery, and that such Heir and Heirs until such time as he or they shall have sued their Livery, or might conveniently have sued their Livery, shall be thereof clearly discharged, and that such Officer or Officers, Lessees or Committees, shall upon request made, pay the same to such mean Lords, they giving to such Officer, Lessee, or Committee, a suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Acquittance or Acquittances for the receipt of the same, and that such payment thereof made with Acquittance or Acquittances thereof shewed, shall be to such Officers a sufficient Discharge in that behalf, any law, usage or custom heretofore had or used to the contrary notwithstanding. Provided always, and it is Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That this Act or any thing therein conteined, shall not in any wise extend to any Inquisition or Office taken or found at any time before the end of this present Parliament, nor to hinder, prejudice or take away the title, interest or possession of our Sovereign Lord the King, or of any other person or persons grown or comen by virtue, mean or occasion of any Inquisition or Office taken or found be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the same time, but that as well our said Sovereign Lord the King as all other person and persons having any Title, Estate, or Possession, by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, mean, or occasion of any inquisition or office found before the same time, shall and may have, hold and enjoy the same in like manner and form, as though this Act had never been had or made, any thing in the same Act to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding. Provided always, and it is Enacted by the Authority aforesaid, That in all such cases as any person or persons shall be enabled by this Act to have any Traverse, that then he or they, that shall pursue such Traverse, shall first exhibit his or their Bill in his Majesties Court of Wards and Liveries, thereby praying to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the same, and being thereunto admitted by the said Court, shall and may then proceed to his traverse, and not otherwise, any law, usage or custom to
<pb facs="tcp:206621:7"/> the contrary notwithstanding. Provided also, and it is Enacted by the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority abovesaid, That if after any judgment shall be given upon any Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verse that shall be tendered or sued by virtue or mean of this Act, it shall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by any matter of Record, that the King hath any other former Title, Right or Interest, to the Mannors, Lands, Tenements or other Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, mentioned in the same Traverse, that then the same Title, Right and Interest, shall be saved to the King, the said Traverse and iudgment there upon given any wise notwithstanding.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. An Act against Discontinuances of Writs of Error in the Court of Exchequer, and for the better expedition in giving judgment therein.</head>
               <p>WHereas by an Estatute made within the Kingdom of <hi>England,</hi> in the One and thirtieth Year of the Reign of King <hi>Edward</hi> the Third, It is Enacted that upon complaint concerning error made in the Exchequer, touching the King or other persons, the Lord Chancellour and Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer shall do to come before them in any Chamber of Council nigh the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer the Record and process of the Exchequer, and taking to them such Iustices and other sage persons, as to them shall be thought meet, shall hear and determine such errors, as by the said Estatute more at large appeareth; And whereas those two being great Officers of the Realm are imployed not onely in their several Offices and places of Iustice elsewhere, but also for other weighty affairs of this Realm in Council attendant on the person of the King's Lievtenant, or other chief Governour, and otherwise, and many times upon sudden warning are called away in such wise, as they both many times, and sometimes neither of them can be present in the Exchequer at their day of adjournment, or other proceedings in such suit of error, and then by not coming of them at the day of adjournment or other times of proceeding, every such Writ of error depending, is by the Laws of this Realm discontinued, or the party cannot proceed but must begin his suit of new, to the great loss of the party, and hindrance of Iustice: For remedy whereof, be it Ordained and Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and the Commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Assembled, and by Authority of the same, that upon complaint of such errors in the Exchequer the Lord Chancellour, and Lord Treasurer or in his absence the Vice-Treasurer shall have power by this Act to hear and deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine such errors as by the said Statute the Lord Chancellour, &amp; Lord Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer were appointed to hear &amp; determine: that the not convening of the Lord Chancellour and Lord Treasurer or either of them at the day of Adjourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in any such suit of error depending by virtue of the said former Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, shall not be any discontinuance of any such Writ of error, but if both the chief Iustices of either Bench, or any one of the said great Officers, the Lord Chancellour or Lord Treasurer, or the Vice-Treasurer shall come to the Exchequer Chamber, and there be present at the day of Adjournment, in such suit of error it shall be no discontinuance, but the suit shall proceed in Law to al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> intents and purposes, as if both the Lord Chancellour and Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surer had comen and been present at the day and place of Adjournment, and also that judgment shall and may be given by the Lord Chancellour, Lord Treasurer or Vice-Treasurer in absence of the Lord Treasurer, and in the presence and by the advice of both the Chief Iustices of either Bench, in every or any such suit or Writ of error, and that all and every such judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments so hereafter to be given, shall be good, valid and effectual in the law to all intents and purposes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb facs="tcp:206621:7"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. An Act for strengthning of Letters Patents past and to be past, upon any of His Majesties Commissions of Grace for the Remedy of defective Titles, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>WHereas the Kings most Excellent Majesty in his special care, grace and goodness towards his loving Subjects of this his Kingdom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> of his own meer and free motion hath of late granted divers Commissions usually called Commissions of Grace for remedy of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fective Titles within this Realm for securing the Estates and Possessions, or pretended or reputed Estates and Possessions of his said Subjects, And whereas divers Lands and Hereditaments, have been past or mentioned to have been past, by sundry new Letters Patents respectively upon some one or more of the said Commissions, and some Letters Patents have been past at divers times to one and the same persons, bodies politick or incorporate, of one and the same things, for their more security as well upon some one or more of the said former Commissions, as after upon the later Commission of Grace bearing date at <hi>Canterbury</hi> in the Realm of <hi>England,</hi> the first day of <hi>September</hi> in the Fourteenth year of his said Majesties Reign, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as also a great part of the Lands and Hereditaments within this Kingdom, which are not yet past upon any of the said Commissions of Grace, and some part of those lands and Hereditaments which are already past, or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to have been past upon some of the said former Commissions of Grace, but not upon the later, may hereafter be past either upon the now Commissi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Grace, or upon some other like Commission or Commissions which hereafter shall or may be granted; and whereas likewise his most Sacred Majesty hath been graciously pleased to secure his said Subjects estates, or pretended, or reputed estates past or to be past as aforesaid, or mentioned to be past upon the said Commissions, or some or any of them, by diverse advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Statutes Enacted here the last Parliament in the <hi>Tenth year</hi> of his prosperous Reign; and whereas his Highness in his further Princely care and abundant Favour and Grace towards his good and loving Subjects of this Realm for the better securing of their several Estates and Possessions and pretended or reputed Estates and Possessions, is graciously pleased now that it be Enacted, And be it Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same that all and every Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents which are already past or hereafter shall be past under the great Seal of this Kingdom of <hi>Ireland</hi> of any Castles, Honors, Mannors, Towns, Villages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, Franchises, Liberties, Immuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, or other Hereditaments, Spiritual or Temporal, within this Kingdom, of what nature, quality, kind or sort soever, by virtue or pretence of or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference unto any Commission of Grace now in being, or hereafter to be within this Kingdom or any other former Commission or Commissions, granted since the beginning of his now Majesties Reign, to any person or persons, bodies politick or incorporate, Spiritual or Temporal, other than those Letters Patents, past, or hereafter to be past, at diverse times, of one and the same things or of one and the same and other things, to one and the same persons, Bodies politick or incorporate their Heirs Successors, Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or Assigns respectively, or to their or any of their use or uses, or in trust for them, or any of them, or with Remainder or Remainders over or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise by virtue or pretence of, or reference unto any such former and later
<pb facs="tcp:206621:8"/> Commission or Commissions of Grace, or which hereafter shall or may be past, by virtue or pretence of, or reference unto the Commission of grace now in being or any other Commission of Grace hereafter to be and likewise all and every Clause Article, Sentence, Word, matter and thing in every of the said Letters Patents contained or mentioned or to be contained or mentioned respectively, other than in the said later Letters Patents, shall be by authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this present Parliament Enacted, and to be and shall be deemed, and adjudged to be good, sufficient, effectual, and indefeazable to all intents, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structions and purposes in manner following (that is to say) for and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning all and every the Lands, Liberties, Franchizes, Immunities, and other Hereditaments and Premisses, whatsoever lying or being within every or any of the late Plantations within this Kingdom made by our late So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lady <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> our late most gracious Lord King <hi>James,</hi> and made or to be made by the Kings most Excellent Majesty that now is, or by any of them as well against his Majesty his Heirs and Successors as against all and every other person, and persons Bodies politick and incorporate as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well Spiritual as Temporal whatsoever; And for and concerning all the rest of the Premisses against his Majesty his Heirs and Successors onely notwithstanding any defect whatsoever, or any Statute, Ordinance, Law Cause, matter, or thing, which might or may any way impeach, infeeble, avoid or destroy any of the said Letters Patents in all or any point or points whatsoever for and according to such, and the same Estate, and Estates, with Remainder and Remainders over or otherwise, and to such and the same use and uses, and in such and the same manner and form according to the true meaning and purport of every of the same Letters Patents as are or shall be Limited Mentioned or declared in every of the Letters Patents aforesaid respectively, And that aswel all and every such Patentee and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentees as those in remainder limited or declared, in or by such Letters Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents, their and every of their Heirs, Successors, Executors, Administrators, and Assigns, and every of them respectively from and immediatly after the new passing or sealing of every or any such Letters Patents past or to be past as aforesaid shall and may thenceforth peaceably and quietly have, hold, posses and injoy, all and singular and every the Lands, Tenements, Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditaments, and other the Premisses lying or being within all and every, or any of the Plantations aforesaid and specified or mentioned in any of the said Letters Patents to have been granted or hereafter to be granted, or mentioned to be granted as aforesaid as well against his Majesty his Heirs and Successors as against all and every other person and persons Bodies po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick and incorporate Spiritual and Temporal whatsoever, and all other the Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments, and Premisses mentioned to have been granted or hereafter to be granted, or mentioned to be granted in any of the said Letters Patents as aforesaid onely against his Majesty his Heirs and Successors for such Estate and Estates with Remainder and Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders over or otherwise and to such use and uses, and in such manner and form as are, or shall be limited, mentioned, or declared in every of the said letters patents respectively, freed and discharged of and from and all Rents, sums of money, Conditions, Covenants, Incumbrances, and Demands whatsoever, other than the Rents, Reservations, Services, Conditions, Covenants, and Charges, which are, or shall be reserved, or saved or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned to be reserved or saved in or by every of the said Letters Patents res<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectively. And concerning such Letters Patents as have already been past or hereafter shall be past diverse times of one and the same things or of one, and the same and other things to one and the same persons, Body Politick, or incorporate their Heirs, Successors, or Assigns respectively, or to their or
<pb facs="tcp:206621:8"/> any of their vse or vses or in trust for them, or any of them, or with Remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or Remainders, over or otherwise, by virtue, or pretence of or reference unto any such former and later Commission and Commissions of Grace, or which hereafter shall or may be past by virtue of pretence of or reference un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Commission of Grace now in being or any other Commission of Grace hereafter to be; Be it Enacted by the Authority aforesaid that onely the later of such Letters Patents, and all and every Clause, Article, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, Word, matter and thing in every such later Letters Patents contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned or specified, or to be conteined or specified, be and for ever shall be deemed and adjudged to be good sufficient, effectual and indefeazable to all intents, Constructions and purposes in manner and form following (that is to say) for and concerning all and every the Lands, Liberties, Franchises, Immu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, and other Hereditaments, and premisses whatsoever in such later Letters Patents conteined or specified, or to be conteined or specified lying or being within every or any the late Plantations made by our late Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Lady Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> our late most gracious Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> and made or to be made by the Kings most Excellent Majesty that now is, or by any of them aswel against his Majesty his Heirs and Successors, as against all and every other person and persons, Bodies politick and incorporate as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wel Spiritual as Temporal whatsoever, and for and concerning all the rest of the Premisses in such later Letters Patents contained or specified alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy made or hereafter to be made, against his Majesty his Heirs and Succes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors onely, notwithstanding any defect whatsoever, or any Statute, Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Law, Cause, matter or thing which might or may any way impeach, infeeble, avoid, or destroy any of the said later letters patents in all or any point or points whatsoever, for and according to such and the same Estate and Estates with Remainder and Remainders over or otherways, and to such and the same use and uses, and in such and the same manner and form according to the true meaning and purport of every of the same later Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents as are, or shall be limited, mentioned, or declared respectively in every of the said later letters patents, and that aswel all and every such later Patentee and Patentees as those in remainder limited, or declared in or by such later letters patents, their and every of their Heirs Successors, Executors, Administrators, and Assigns respectively from and immediatly after the new passing or sealing of every or any such later letters patents past or to be past (as aforesaid) shall and may thenceforth peaceably and qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly have, hold, possess, and enjoy all and singular the Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, and other the premisses lying or being within all and every or any the Plantations aforesaid, and specified or mentioned in any of the said later Letters Patents to have been granted or hereafter to be granted, or mentioned to be granted as aforesaid as well against his Majesty his Heirs and Successors as against all and every other person and persons, Bodies politick and incorporate, Spiritual and Temporal whatsoever, and all other the Lands, Tenements, Hereditaments and Premisses mentioned to have been granted, or hereafter to be granted or mentioned to be granted in any of the said later Letters Patents (as aforesaid) onely against his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors for such Estate, and Estates, with Remainder and Remainders over or otherwise, and to such use and uses, and in such manner and form as are or shall be limited, mentioned, or declared in every of the said later Letters Patents respectively, freed and discharged of and from all Rents, sums of money, Conditions, Covenants, Incumbrances and demands whatsoever, other than the Rents, Reservations, Services, Conditions, Covenants, and charges which are, or shall be reserved, or saved or mentioned to be reserved or saved, in or by e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of the said later Letters Patents respectively, and likewise that every
<pb facs="tcp:206621:9"/> tenure now or heretofore mentioned, or hereafter to be mentioned in any Letters Patents already made, or hereafter to be made, or in any other Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord or Records to be of the King by Knights Service in <hi>capite,</hi> or by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Knights Service and not in <hi>capite,</hi> or <hi>de capitalibus Dominis,</hi> if the same prove to be a tenure of the King by Knights Service in <hi>capite,</hi> or by Common Knights Service and not in <hi>capite,</hi> wherein no mention is or shall be made by what part of a Knights Fee, the same tenure is or shall be by the Authority aforesaid Enacted and be declared, explained and adjudged to be a tenure in <hi>capite,</hi> by one whole Knights Fee onely, if the Land and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditaments mentioned or to be mentioned in the same Letters Patents, or other Record or Records to be held by either of those tenures amount un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the clear yearly value of four hundred pounds <hi>English</hi> money, and no more, and so <hi>pro rata</hi> more or less according to the clear yearly value of the Lands, or Hereditaments, held or to be held, by such tenure or tenures; provided always that the reliefs of Dukes, Marquesses, Earls, Viscounts, and Barons, shall be and continue as antiently they have been before the making of this Act. And be it further Enacted, Adjudged, and Declared, by the Kings most Excellents Majesty and Authority aforesaid that his said Majesty, his Heirs and Successors respectively be and shall be deemed, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged seised and vested in the actual and real seisin and possession of a good lawful indefeazable and absolute Estate to him or them, his or their Heirs, and Successors, in right of his and their Imperial Crown of and in all and singular and every the Castles, Honours, Mannors, Towns, Villages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, scituate, lying or being in the several Counties of <hi>Tyrone, Ardmagh, Donegal, Fermanagh, Cavan, Letrim,</hi> and <hi>Longford,</hi> and likewise of all the several Territories, precincts of Land and Countries commonly known or called by the name or names of, <hi>Ely O Carrol, alias O Carrols</hi> Country, <hi>Fercal, alias O Molloies</hi> Country, <hi>Kilcoursie, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ias Foxes</hi> Country, <hi>Delvin Coghlan, alias in Coghlans</hi> Country, in the Kings County upper <hi>Ossory, alias</hi> Mac <hi>GilPatricks</hi> Country, and <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>regan, alias O Doynes</hi> Country, in the Queens County, the <hi>Murrowes, Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>hobuck, Clamhenrick, Fer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>anhaman, Killekeel, alias</hi> Mac <hi>Vadocks</hi> Country, <hi>Kilecoolenelin, alias Coolenelem, alias</hi> Mac <hi>Morris</hi> his Country, <hi>Kenshelaghs, Macdamores</hi> Country, and <hi>Brackenagh</hi> in the County of <hi>Wexford, Ranelagh, alias Conleranel</hi> the <hi>Birns</hi> Country, <hi>Cosha, Shillela</hi> and the <hi>Fertry, alias Farter</hi> in the County of <hi>Wickloe,</hi> and <hi>Idough, alias Odough, alias Brenan</hi> in the County of <hi>Kilkeny,</hi> and also of all the several Towns, Villages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments known, esteemed, reputed, or usual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called plantation lands, in or near the Territories or Countries of <hi>Clon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colman alias O Melaghlins</hi> Country in the County of <hi>Westmeath,</hi> and in or near the territory and Country of <hi>Farran O Neal</hi> in or near the County of <hi>Wexford,</hi> and of and in the Towns, and Lands, of <hi>Tourboy,</hi> in or near the Territory of <hi>Ranelagh</hi> aforesaid, and also of all and singular the Castles, Honours, Mannors, Towns, Villages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, in the several Counties of <hi>Watersord, Cork, Limerick, Kerry,</hi> and <hi>Typerary,</hi> usually called, or reputed as Plantation Lands or heretofore past or mentioned to have been past by Letters Patents to any Brittish undertaker or undertakers by birth, bloud, or descent, their Heirs or Assigns respectively as Plantation Lands, at every such time and times respectively whensoever any of the same before mentioned Castles, Honors, Mannors, Towns, Villages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, and Heredita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, shall be within the space of five years next ensuing the end of this present Session of Parliament new passed, granted, confirmed, released or assured or mentioned to be new passed, granted, confirmed, released or assured
<pb facs="tcp:206621:9"/> to any person or persons Bodies politick or incorporate Spiritual or Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral respectively by Letters Patents under the great Seal of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom by virtue or pretence of or reference unto any such Commission of Grace now being or hereafter to be within this Realm being either former Patentees or reputed Inheritors or proprietors or by former Assignation, Distribution or appointment have taken the profits thereof, their Heirs, Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessors, Executors, Administrators, or Assigns respectively, or being some person or persons in trust for them, or any of them, or nominated or appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed or to be nominated, or appointed, to be trusted for them or any of them, and that from and immediately after the passing or sealing, of every, or any such Letters Patents in manner last before specified to any of the said per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son or persons, Bodies politick or incorporate, that as well all and every such Patentee and Patentees, as those in remainder limited, or declared in or by such Letters Patents their and every of their Heirs, Successors, Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutors, Administrators, and Assigns and every of them respectively, shall and may for ever thenceforth peaceably and quietly have, hold, possess, and enjoy all and singular the same Castles, Honours, Mannors, Towns, Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, before specified which shall be granted, confirmed, released, or assured or mentioned to be granted, confirmed, released, or assured as aforesaid for such, and the same Estate and Estates with Remainder and Remainders over, or otherwise, and to such and the same use and uses, and in such and the same manner and form as shall be limited, mentioned, or declared, in every of the said Letters Patents, respectively to be made as aforesaid, aswel against his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors, as against all and every other person and persons Bodies politick and incorporate, aswel Spiritual as Temporal whatsoever, freed and discharged of and from all Rents, sums of money, Conditions, Covenants, Incumbrances, and demands whatsoever, other than the Rents, Reservations, Services, Conditions, Covenants, and charges which shall be reserved, or saved or mentioned to be reserved or sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in or by every of the said Letters Patents respectively, and that all and every the said Letters patents aswel of all and every of the same last before specified Castles, Honours, Mannors, Towns, Villages, Hamlets, Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, as of all and singular the residue of the premisses before mentioned, and every part thereof, and all and every Clause, Article, Sentence, Word, Matter and thing, in them and every of them conteined or specified, or to be conteined or specified, shall be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways taken, construed, and expounded, most liberally and beneficially for the best advantage, benefit, and availe, of all and every such patentee and patentees, and those in Remainder and Remainders, or otherwise limited or declared in or by such Letters patents, their and every of their Heirs, Successors, Executors, Administrators, and Assigns, and every of them respectively, against his Majesty, his Heirs and Successors for ever. And be it further Enacted, adjudged, and declared by the authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty aforesaid, that no words of Covenant, pact, agreement, or Command, nor any Clause, Sentence, Article, or Words purporting in substance a Covenant, pact, agreement, or command, mentioned or to be mentioned, in any the aforesaid Letters patents past or to be past by virtue or pretence of or reference unto any of the Commission or Commissions aforesaid, shall be construed or expounded as a proviso or condition, and that the breach thereof or the doing of any Act contrary to any thing commanded, agreed or covenanted for, in or by any clause, article, sentence, or words in any such Letters Patents, or the not doing or misdoing of any thing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in or thereby required, or enjoyned, shall not give cause either of avoidance
<pb facs="tcp:206621:10"/> or impeachment of any of the same Letters Patents in part, or in the whole or of fine, imprisonment, or other punishment of the parties delin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, or of any other forfeiture, penalty, or loss, but onely that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jesty, his Heirs and Successors may recover such his or their reasonable damages for the same by action of covenant in any of his Majesties Courts, or English Bill in the Court of Exchequer here, as in case of Breach of Covenant are usual to be awarded or given in actions of Covenants brought at the common Law, in any of the ordinary Courts of Iustice for or up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on like breach, omission, or not doing, or misdoing (as aforesaid) and no more nor otherwise; Provided always that this last clause, or any therein contained shall not bar his Majesty his Heirs or Successors, of any entry or reseisure for breach of any express condition in any the said Letters pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents expressed; And be it further Enacted, and declared by the Authority aforesaid that aswel this present Act made for the strengthning of Letters patents as also the three several former Acts Enacted to the same or like purpose the last Parliament in the <hi>tenth year</hi> of his Majesties now pros<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous Reign, one whereof is Intituled, <hi>An Act for confirming of Letters Patents hereafter to be past upon his Majesties Commission of Grace for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy of defective Titles,</hi> another is <hi>An Act of Explanation of the former Statute last before mentioned,</hi> and the third Intituled, <hi>An Act for securing of the Estates of the Undertakers, Servitors, natives, and others holding Lands, Tenements or Hereditaments in all and every the Plantations made by our late Sovereign Lady Queen Elizabeth, or by our late most gracious Lord King James, or the Kings most Excellent Majesty that now is, in the several Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Cork, Waterford, Limerick, Kerry, Tipperary, Wexford, Wickloe, Kings County, Queens County, Westmeath, Letrim, Longford, Tyrone, Ard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh, Donnegal, Fermanagh, Cavan, and Londonderry;</hi> And all and every Clause, Article, Sentence, Word, Matter, and thing, in these Acts and every of them, conteined, or expressed, shall be expounded and construed most strong against his Majesty his Heirs, and Successors, and most favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably, liberally, and beneficially, to all intents and purposes for the best advantage, benefit and avail of every such patentee and patentees, and those in remainder or use or uses, limited or declared in or by such Letters patents, their and every of their Heirs, Successors, Executors, Admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strators, and Assigns, and every of them respectively to whom any Letters patents have been passed or hereafter shall be past by virtue or pretence of, or reference unto any such Commission or Commissions of grace in man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner before expressed; provided nevertheless and be it Enacted by the Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforesaid that this Act nor any thing therein contained shall not any wise bar or prejudice the Right or Title of any Arch-Bishop, Bishop, Dean, Chapter, Arch-Deacon, Dignitary, Prebendary, Parson, Vicar, or other Spiritual, or Ecclesiastical person to any Mannors, Lands, Tenements, or Hereditaments, being the Inheritance and possession of their respective Churches, or Benefices.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. An Act concerning Clergy.</head>
               <p>FOrasmuch as heretofore some doubt hath been conceived whether the al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowance of Clergy in case of Fellony do in Law acquit the Fellon of all other Fellonies by him formerly committed, for the clearing of which doubt; Be it Enacted and declared by the Kings most Excellent Majesty with the Assent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent Parliament Assembled, and by Authority of the same, that all and
<pb facs="tcp:206621:10"/> every person and persons which shall hereafter be admitted to have the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of his or their Clergy shall notwithstanding his or their admission to the same be put to answer to all other Fellonies whereof he or they shall be hereafter indicted or appealed, and not being thereof before lawfully acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, convicted, attainted, or pardoned, and shall in such manner and form be arraigned, tryed, judged and suffer such Execution for the same, as he or they should have done, if as Clerk or Clerks convict, they had been delivered to the Ordinary, and there had made his or their purgation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. An Act for punishing of Offenders within the County of Dublin, and County of the City of Dublin against the Act for Keepers of Alehouses to be bound by Recognizance.</head>
               <p>WHereas in the late Parliament held in this Kingdom in the <hi>tenth year</hi> of his Majesties Reign that now is, there was a good and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable Law made, intituled, <hi>An Act for Keepers of Alehouses to be bound by Recognizance:</hi> Which Law hath not wrought that good effect within the County of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> that was expected, for that the said Statute directeth that every person or persons offending a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the same should be proceeded against and punished either before the Lord Deputy or other chief Governor or Governors, and the Council of State for the time being, or in his Majesties Court of Exchequer or before the Iustices of Assize at their general assizes, and for that few or none of the Offenders against the Statute have been prosecuted before the Lord Deputy and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, or in his Majesties Court of Exchequer, for that the proceedings in the said Courts are not of so ready dispatch as the presentments befo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e the Iustices of Assize, and for that there are no Iustices of Assize which do ride within the County of <hi>Dublin,</hi> or within the County of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> Be it therefore Enacted by the Authority of this present Parliament, that all and every person and persons dwelling within the County of <hi>Dublin</hi> or the County of the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> offending contrary to the form of the said Statute, shall be proceeded against and punished either before the Lord De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty or other chief Governour or Governours, and Council of State there for the time being, or in his Majesties Court of Exchequer, or before the Iudges of his Majesties Court of Kings Bench or chief place, or before his Majesties Iustices of the peace at the Quarter Sessions, of the said several Counties, who shall have full power and Authority to hear and determine the same, And to the intent the said Law may the better be put in Executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, It is further Enacted by the Authority aforesaid that the Informer which shall cause such presentments, and Informations to be made and prosecuted with effect, shall have the third part of such Fine, as shall be imposed upon such as shall offend, contrary to the purport of the said Statute.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. An Act to discharge and free true Men from all forfeitures for Killing such as attempt to Rob or Murther them.</head>
               <p>FOrasmuch as it hath been questionable that if any evil disposed person or persons, do attempt felloniously to rob or murther, any person or persons in or near any Common highway, Cartway, Horsway, or Footway, or in their Mansions, Messuages, or dwelling places or grounds, or that felloniously do attempt to break any dwelling Houses, in the night or day time should hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen
<pb facs="tcp:206621:11"/> in his or their being in such their fellonious intent and attempt to be slain by him or them whom the said evil doerrs should so attempt to rob, or murther: or by any person or persons being with them in their said dwelling Houses, which the same evil doers should attempt Burgularly, or felloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously to break by night, or by day, whether the said person happening in such Case to slay any such person so attempting to commit such murther, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery, or Burglary, should for the death of such evil disposed person forfeit or loose his goods and Chattels for the same, as any other person should do that by chance medly should happen to kill or slay any other person or in his or their defence, for the declaration of which ambiguity and doubt. Be it Enacted by our Sovereign Lord the King, with the assent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this present Parliament As<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembled, and by the Authority of the same, that if any person or persons at any time hereafter be Indicted or appealed of or for the death of any such evil disposed person or persons attempting to murther or rob as aforesaid or Burgulariously or felloniously to break any Mansion Houses as is above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said that the person or persons so indicted or appealed thereof, and of the same by verdict so found and tryed shall not forfeit or loose any Lands, Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nements, Goods, or Chattels, for the death of any such evil disposed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in such manner slain; but shall be thereof, and for the same fully acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and discharged in like manner as if the same person or persons, shoul be if he or they were lawfully acquitted of the death of the said evil disposed person or persons.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. X. An Act for remedy of errors and defects in Fines and Common Recoveries heretofore leavied acknowledged and suffered.</head>
               <p>FOrasmuch as Fines and Common Recoveries are the best and highest assurances which the Law hath provided for securing of mens Estates, in Lands, Tenements, and Hereditaments, and that partly by reason of the Common Calamity of Wars which for many years disturbed the peace and prosperity of this Kingdom, and partly by reason of the negligences and misprisions of Clerks and Officers in writing engrossing, and prosecuting of such Fines and Recoveries, and the careless keeping of the Records thereof many errors and defects have passed and overslipt therein to the great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of the shaking and weakning of such assurances and Estates contrary to the true meaning of all parties thereunto, for reformation whereof; Be it Enacted by our Sovereign Lord the Kings most Excellent Majesty, the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and the Commons in this present Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment assembled, and by the Authority of the same, that no Fine Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon fines or common Recovery had, leavied, suffered, or passed before the first day of <hi>Easter</hi> Term, in the <hi>first year</hi> of the Reign of the Kings most Excellent Majesty that now is, where the possession of the Lands, and Hereditaments, therein mentioned hath been enjoyed according to the said Fine or Recovery, or the Indentures or other writings declared the uses thereof, shall be reversed by any writ of error but shall be deemed and adjudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed good and effectual in Law, as if the same had been duely and legally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged had leavied, suffered and passed, in all and every the parts there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; any error or defect in matter of Fact or Law whatsoever, or any Law, Statute, Ordinance, or Provision whatsoever to the contrary in any wise notwithstanding: provided always that this Act or any thing therein contained shall not extend unto any Fine or Fines, Proclamati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon Fine or Fines or common Recovery or Recoveries, whereof
<pb facs="tcp:206621:11"/> any writ or writs of error, is or are already brought before the first day of <hi>February</hi> last and now depending in his Majesties Court of chief place here, or Kings Bench in <hi>England,</hi> for reversing or making void of any fines or common Recoveries; Provided further that if any person or persons which are or shall be intituled unto any writ or writs of error, for the reversal of any such Fine or Fines recovery or recoveries be or were within the Age of one and twenty years <hi>Feme covert, non compos mentis,</hi> imprisoned or beyond the Seas, the said first day of <hi>Easter</hi> Term in the said <hi>first year</hi> of his now Majesties Reign or at any time sithence, that then such person or persons shall be at liberty to bring their writ or writs of error so as they bring the same within three years after the end of this Session of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament or within five years next after he or they shall attain their full Age, discovertures coming of sound mind, inlargement out of prison, or coming into this realm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XI. An Act for Endowing of Churches with Gleab Lands.</head>
               <p>WHereas all Beneficiaries with Cure especially Viccars are bound to perpetual residence and yet through the War and confusion of former times in this Kingdom the Ancient Gleabs in many places are so obscured that they cannot be found out: by which means the incumbents are necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to perpetual non residence, Be it therefore Enacted by the King most Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Majesty the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in this Parliament Assembled, and by Authority of the same, that it shall be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any devout person without licence of Mortmain to endow Churches having no Gleabs, or not above ten Acres of Gleab with new Gleab, provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that the Gleab of any one Church so endowed do not exceed forty Acres at the most and that the said Lands be not holden <hi>in capite,</hi> or by Knights service.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. XII. An Act concerning twentieth parts and other sums of mony payable by persons Ecclesiastical.</head>
               <p>WHereas it was Enacted and ordeyned amongst other things in a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament holden at <hi>Dublin,</hi> in the eight and twentieth year of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eight that if any summ of mony being once due by any Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent of any dignity, benefice or promotion Spiritual in the name of a twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part, being lawfully demanded, were not truly contented, and paid to such person or persons as should have the charge of the Collection thereof or their Officers and Ministers at the time of the demand, or within forty days after, that then every such Incumbent after such default certified into the Kings Exchequer in writing, under the Seals of such person or persons as are charged by the said Act with the collection of the said Annuall pension, should be adjudged deprived <hi>(ipso facto)</hi> of all such dignities, benefices and promotions Spiritual as he should have at the time of such certificate to be made or at any time after, so that all such dignities, benefices or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motions should be clearly void of Incumbents in the law to all intents and purposes as if the said Incumbent were indeed dead, which Act be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fitted and accomodated to the state of those times to take away the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign dependance of the Clergy, is become a means often to deprive Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons
<pb facs="tcp:206621:12"/> of their right of presentation, without any default of theirs, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary not being bound to give notice to the Patron, in case of any such o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mission, &amp; for that a meer omission in the Incumbent deserveth not to be so rigorously punished, Be it Enacted by the Kings most Excellent Majesty with the Assent of the Lords Spiritual &amp; Temporal and Commons in this present Parliament Assembled, and by the Authority of the same, that the omission or not payment of the said twentieth parts, Annual Rent, pension, or sum of money after the last day of this present Session shall be no deprivation nor cause of forfeiture or deprivation of any such Incumbent, But that every such Incumbent so failing in the payment of the said An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual Rent or pension shall forfeit to his Majesty for his omission as <hi>(nomine poenae)</hi> the triple value of such twentieth part, Annuall Rent, pension or sum of money as he ought by virtue of the said former Act to have paid and failed in the payment thereof, the said former Act or any thing therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyned to the contrary notwithstanding.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:206621:12"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>